<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "roles.dtd">
<news>
    <post>
        <title>Census Data Collection Integrity Questioned</title>
        <date>Monday, February 26, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/6HR.jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[<p>Rural Women New Zealand have released a media release raising our concerns for how data is being collected in this year's census. </p>
<div>
 <p>Please read the media release below.</p>
 <p><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-size: inherit; font-style: inherit; font-variant-ligatures: inherit; font-variant-caps: inherit;">CENSUS DATA COLLECTION INTEGRITY QUESTIONED</strong> <br> </p>
</div>
<div>
 <p>This year’s census is in danger of not providing the data needed to make good decisions, says Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ).</p>
 <p>“Whilst we understand and support the excitement of capturing our census data online, our concern is that many people still do not have access to internet while others might not have the capability or capacity to do so,” says National President, Fiona Gower.</p>
 <p>“The timing of the delivery of access code letters, which indicate that New Zealanders can opt for paper forms presents challenges for our rural communities, given that delivery of mail is taking longer and might only be delivered three days a week.</p>
 <p>“The chances of a rural household without internet or with unreliable internet, receiving census paper forms in time for Tuesday, 6 March is slim, and that is concerning.</p>
 <p>“RWNZ is doing everything possible to ensure our networks are aware of the new way of doing the Census although surely more thought should have gone in to how the valuable information about the lives and status of New Zealanders would be collected.</p>
 <p>“Maybe this year, there could have been a concerted effort to use both electronic collection and paper collection to ensure integrity of the data,” says Ms Gower.</p>
 <p><strong>Ends</strong> </p>
 <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong> </p>
 <p>Please contact the National Office for more information.</p>
 <p>&nbsp;</p>
 <p>&nbsp;</p>
 <p>National Office</p>
 <p>Rural Women New Zealand</p>
 <p>&nbsp;</p>
 <p><a href="/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" class="__cf_email__" data-cfemail="76131807031f041f130536040304171a01191b13185819041158180c">[email&nbsp;protected]</a></p>
 <p>04 473 5524</p>
 <br>
 <p>&nbsp;</p>
 <p>&nbsp;</p>
 <p>(<em>image source: www.census.govt.nz)</em> </p>
</div>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>CSW62 Well Underway</title>
        <date>Thursday, March 15, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/Sticks and Stones Ashley Smith, Fiona.JPG</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[<p>(<em>Pictured: Sticksn'Stones Chairperson Ashleigh Smith with RWNZ National President, Fiona Gower in the UN General Assembly at the CSW62 Opening on Monday).&nbsp;</em> </p>
<p><em>&nbsp;</em>The opening of the 62nd Session of the Commission on the Status of Women (CSW62) was held on Monday, 12 March 2018 at the United Nations in New York. The Commission's priority theme for this year is 'Challenges and opportunities in achieving gender equality and the empowerment of rural women and girls'. The work of the Commission is to review the progress made by governments to improve the lives of women and girls in rural areas.</p>
<p>CSW62 is being held in the UN General Assembly and 175 member and observer states are represented. Along with the member states there are 10,000 delegates from 400 Non-Government Organisations (NGO) attending numerous events as part of the CSW62's activities.</p>
<p>The day commenced with the session being opened by the CSW Chair Ambassador Geraldine Byrne Nason from Ireland. She is also Ireland's Permanent Representative at the UN. Her address was followed by the UN Secretary-General Antonio Guterres, and the President of the UN General Assembly Miroslav Lajcak. Other speakers included the Chair of the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women (CEDAW), a Representative of the Youth, and a Special Rapporteur on violence against women, its causes and consequences. <br> </p>
<p>National Chair, Penny Mudford also attended the opening in her role as Civil Society Representative on the New Zealand Government delegation. Both Fiona and Penny attended the opening inside the General Assembly where only government delegations and selected NGO delegates are eligible to attend. It was a great privilege that RWNZ was represented in person at the opening of CSW62.</p>
<p>CSW62 runs until Friday, 23 March 2018 where it is expected to culminate in an Outcome Document which will capture the agreed outcomes in relation to rural women and girls for governments to implement resulting from the work done at this session of the Commission.</p>
<p>New Zealand also held a side event led by Dr Jackie Blue, NZ Human Rights Commission responsible for Womens Rights. The panel comprised Minister for Women Hon Julie Anne Genter, Renee Graham (Ministry for Women Chief Executive), Fiona Gower, Jo Finer (Fonterra), plus representatives from Argentina and Australia. The panel spoke on the topic of Case Studies of Economic Empowerment of Rural Women in New Zealand, Australia, and Argentina. The session was full with over 100 delegates from all around the world attending the panel session. There was keen interest in our message.</p>
<p><em>National Chair, Penny Mudford.&nbsp;</em> </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em>&nbsp;</em> </p>
<p><em>&nbsp;</em> </p>&nbsp;
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Future Farms Conference 2018</title>
        <date>Wednesday, March 21, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/20180313_172844.jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[
<p>The 5<sup style="font-family: inherit; font-style: inherit; font-variant-ligatures: inherit; font-variant-caps: inherit; font-weight: inherit;">th</sup> New Zealand Future Farms Conference was held on Tuesday, 12 – Wednesday, 13 March last week in Palmerston North. The event focused on the direction of farming in New Zealand with insights on the Digital Farmer; developing and diversifying on farm practice; farming’s role in high value food; farm health and strategy, and navigating change. <br> </p>
<p>Board Member, Janet Williams presented on the <em>Future of Farming – Navigating Change and Developing Strategy, </em>focusing on developing rural communities to support the future farmer.</p>
<p>Janet talked about needing a significant increase of skilled people to double the exports by 2025, and emphasised the need to work smarter as primary industries uses 50% of New Zealand land and there is no more room for expansion.</p>
<p>Her examples of strengthening rural communities included Farmlands giving free rugby tickets for a Friday afternoon in Te Kuiti where majority of the small towns population had come to watch.</p>
<p>The game between the Blues and Chiefs was enjoyed by all and the Farmlands Rural Legends Shield was taken home by the Blues (Te Kuiti is the home town of the late Sir Colin Meads). Another example she gave was a local rural school, that planned their swimming sports where unfortunately a plumbing fault led to the pool having no water. Te Awamutu Fonterra filled their tankers with town supply water that they paid for to fill the school pool so the swimming sports could go ahead, and was an enjoyable family day.</p>
<p>She spoke of members who helped after the Kaikoura earthquake, and the Aftersocks campaign which sought to help those who had been affected by the repercussions of the earthquake and contributed to a fund for future adverse events relief. She encouraged people to purchase Aftersocks through the website and at the Central District Fieldays.</p>
<p>RWNZ has provided support (through donations and Aftersocks sales) to people in the Kaikoura area following the 2016 earthquake and those affected by the flooding in Edgecumbe, South Auckland and the Waikato.</p>
<p>Janet emphasised the importance of children being the involved in rural community events and activities such as the Rural Games which were held in Palmerston North prior to Future Farms, with a section – ‘KidsnCountry’. With competitive events such as rolling bales of hay, sack races and tree climbing, all children were able to have fun.</p>
<p>She spoke of St Pauls Collegiate School in Hamilton who are teaching years 12 and 13 Agribusiness, and the rural industries and businesses who are supporting these classes. December last year saw this course was accredited as a NZQA subject. Last year there were 37 agribusiness students in year 13, and around 30 went into tertiary agribusiness study. This year saw 93 students at St Pauls College in years 12 and 13 taking Agribusiness; they are part of the 500 students in 35 schools across New Zealand studying the subject. It is expected that 1500 students will study Agribusiness in 2019, these students are the future of the rural sector where they will bring modern approaches, become leaders, and market our value through adding export products.</p>
<p>Janet talked of boarding allowances, bursaries and sponsorship available to those from rural communities and/or wishing to pursue tertiary study in Agriculture or similar fields, including 16 of these from RWNZ. She gave light to alternate study or apprenticeship options for school leavers and those perhaps wanting a career change or gain new skills. Reliable and accessible internet is crucial for talented young people to collect the data necessary for precise farming decisions.</p>
<p>She concluded with emphasising the importance of education and technology, along with having resilient strong vibrant rural people to ensure the farming future can grow from strength to strength.</p>
<p>Dame Margaret Millard was at the conference, and her presence was widely appreciated by other delegates. The conference also provided great networking opportunities.</p>
<p>Although smaller than last years, the Future Farms Conference was more interactive, particularly when Minister for Agriculture and Rural Communities, Hon Damien O’Connor dropped by. It was great to see him take a seat on stage and join in on a panel discussion.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>125 Years Since the Vote and Rural Women Still Struggle</title>
        <date>Thursday, March 22, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/DSC_5630 (1).jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[<p><i>(Pictured: RWNZ Board Member and Health convenor, Margaret Pittaway)</i> </p>
<p><i>&nbsp;</i>Rural Women New Zealand are concerned with New Zealand's midwifery shortage, particularly for rural women. Please read our media release below in response to the current media regarding this issue. Board Member and Health convenor, Margaret Pittaway, has been working hard to ensure our concerns for this issue are heard.&nbsp; <br> </p>
<p>You can find the relevant media&nbsp;<strong style="font-family: inherit; font-size: inherit; font-style: inherit; font-variant-ligatures: inherit; font-variant-caps: inherit;"><a href="https://www.stuff.co.nz/business/farming/101874933/shortage-of-rural-midwives-amid-concerns-they-are-not-paid-enough">here</a>.</strong> </p>
<p><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-size: inherit; font-style: inherit; font-variant-ligatures: inherit; font-variant-caps: inherit;">&nbsp;</strong> </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>125 YEARS SINCE THE VOTE AND RURAL WOMEN STILL STRUGGLE</strong> </p>
<p>It’s ironic that in the 125th year of suffrage, New Zealand women are struggling to gain and retain health services, says Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ).</p>
<p>“New Zealand is still hailed as a world leader because New Zealand women won their right to vote in 1893, the first nation in the world, however, we are behind in maternity care,” says Board Member and Health convenor, Margaret Pittaway. </p>
<p>“RWNZ has been observing the developing dilemma for midwives and those they care for, with increasing concern.</p>
<p>“Rural midwives are simply not receiving a living wage due to the expectation they travel many more miles to visit patients than their urban counterparts.</p>
<p>“RWNZ holds grave fears for the wellbeing and safety of rural mums-to-be – decisions on maternal care are putting the mother’s life and the life and intellect of new born babies at risk. </p>
<p>“On top of this, is the insidious progression in the closure of small community hospitals and maternity units in the belief that centralisation of essential services is the best method.</p>
<p>“RWNZ firmly believes that not only is it vital to retain community hospitals for the wellbeing of our new mothers and families, but is vital for the sustainability of rural communities.</p>
<p>“The Government needs to empower rural communities by urgently addressing the crisis in rural health services, particularly resignations as midwives seek better and more attractive opportunities,” says Mrs Pittaway.</p>
<p>Ends</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>International Womens Day &amp; Suffrage125</title>
        <date>Friday, March 23, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/International Women's Day Speakers.jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[<p>Thursday, 8 March marked this year's International Women's Day. As this year also celebrates 125 years since women in New Zealand won the the right to vote, the day was marked with significance. </p>
<p>Wednesday, 7 March was the launch of the Suffrage125 celebrations which was held at Government House and was attended by RWNZ Board Chair, Penny Mudford, Chief Executive Officer, Penelope England and Office Manager, Felicity Bunny. The launch was hosted by the Governor General, and RWNZ Patron Dame Patsy Reddy. The event was MC'd by journalist, Mihingarangi Forbes, and guest speakers included Minister for Women, Hon Julie Anne Genter and 2017 Young New Zealander of the Year, Rez Gardi.</p>
<p>The following day, Thursday, 8 March marked International Women's Day celebrations. RWNZ attended a breakfast at Parliament hosted by Zonta Wellington and the UN Women. RWNZ Chief Executive Officer Penelope England, and Communications, Marketing & Events Assistant, Catherine Stabb both attended the event. </p>
<p>Discussion topics at the event included recognition of the milestones made by women in New Zealand and the challenges that we still face. Rt Hon Helen Clark spoke of her successes, the obstacles she has faced and the how her rural background contributed to her personal strength, saying "rural people have to be very resilient".</p>
<p>Watch Rt Hon Helen Clark's Q&A with National Council of Women CEO Dr Gill Greer at the breakfast through the link <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=youtu.be&v=j9eRDV3Nc2k&app=desktop">here</a>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em>(Pictured below: Executive Officer Women’s Institute - Colleen Dryden, National Board Chair - Penny Mudford ONZM, National President Women’s Institute – Kay Hart, RWNZ Chief Executive Officer – Penelope England at the Suffrage125 launch at Government House.)</em> </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span class="CSJM-image-replacement" data-src="https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/20180307_120142.jpg"></span> <br> </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Rural Communities Deserve Better Technology</title>
        <date>Wednesday, April 04, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/RWNZ Logo blue.jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[
<p>RWNZ has released a media release responding to the introduction of the 5G network in New Zealand.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Please read relevant media <a href="http://ruralwomennewzealand.createsend1.com/t/d-l-ohyklul-l-y/">here</a>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div>
 <div>
  <div>
   <p><strong>RURAL COMMUNITIES DESERVE BETTER TECHNOLOGY</strong> </p>
   <p>Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ) are concerned that the roll-out of the 5G network short-changes rural New Zealand as many still struggle with basic cell phone coverage. </p>
   <p>“The news that 5G cell phone technology will be rolled out by 2020 is great for some but not for all, and that is what bothers us,” says RWNZ Board Member and Technology Portfolio Convenor, Rachael Dean.</p>
   <p>“Many of our rural communities do not have internet or cell phone access at all, let alone that of a high quality standard and the 5G roll-out seems yet another example of doing the easy stuff at the expense of rural New Zealand.</p>
   <p>“Approximately half of New Zealand has no cell phone coverage due to geography which leads to isolation and inability to connect in this ever-increasing digital world – and this is not good enough.</p>
   <p>“Rural New Zealand deserves high quality technology given the economy’s reliance on primary industries and tourism based in rural areas.</p>
   <p>“New Zealand cannot afford for anyone to be left behind in the digital age.</p>
   <p>“This lack of consideration of the impact on rural New Zealand is why it is so important for businesses and the Government to rural proof their decisions,” says Ms Dean.</p>
   <p>Ends</p>
   <p>&nbsp;</p>
   <p>For further information, please contact National Office.&nbsp;</p>
   <p>&nbsp;</p>
   <p>National Office&nbsp;</p>
   <p>Rural Women New Zealand <br>04 473 5524 <br><a href="/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" class="__cf_email__" data-cfemail="a3c6cdd2d6cad1cac6d0e3d1d6d1c2cfd4cccec6cd8dccd1c48dcdd9">[email&nbsp;protected]</a></p>
   <br>
   <p>&nbsp;</p>
  </div>
 </div>
</div>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Rural women need to be involved in decision making.</title>
        <date>Friday, April 06, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/Penny Mudford.jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[<p>Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ) has released a media release today following RWNZ's oral submission on the Trusts Bill.&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Please read the media release below.&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>RURAL WOMEN NEED TO BE INVOLVED IN DECISION MAKING</strong> </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ) influenced positive change for rural families and communities recently, through their oral submission to Parliament on the Trusts Bill. </p>
<p>“RWNZ submitted that both a rural impact and gender impact analysis be conducted on the legislation and intersectionality so that the Bill does not discriminate against women in any way,” says RWNZ National Chair, Penny Mudford.</p>
<p>“RWNZ research indicates that women can be shut out of a share of the family farm through old trusts that fail to acknowledge them in the family as beneficiaries. </p>
<p>“This can lead to women being discriminated against in the dissolution of a relationship where a trust is used to exclude them from a share in the family farm or farm business.</p>
<p>"These situations should not be happening in 2018 and we urge the government to uphold the international instruments and outcome statements when updating legislation such as with the Trusts Bill currently before the Justice Select Committee.</p>
<p>"In particular, the agreed conclusions that came out of the United Nations 62nd session of the Commission on the Status of Women, which were held in New York in March 2018, make it abundantly clear that government's policies and legislation should not disproportionately disadvantage women and girls living in the rural sector. </p>
<p>"Since trusts are a common type of farm ownership structure in New Zealand we need to be sure they are not being used to disadvantage those who would otherwise be entitled to a share of the farm asset through relationship property or inheritance if the asset was not held in trust," says Ms Mudford. </p>
<p>Ends</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>If you wish to read our oral submission, you can find it <a href="/LiteratureRetrieve.aspx?ID=239890">here</a>.&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<br>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Another setback for health and wellbeing of rural communities.</title>
        <date>Friday, April 06, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/medical-doctor-1236728 squarebig.jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[<p>Rural Women New Zealand has today released a media release following the announcement that the Rural Health Alliance Aotearoa New Zealand (RHAANZ) will move to shut down if it does not receive funding.</p>
<p>Read the announcement <a href="https://www.ruralnewsgroup.co.nz/rural-news/rural-general-news/govt-may-force-nz-rural-health-organisation-to-close">here</a>.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>ANOTHER SET BACK FOR THE HEALTH AND WELLBEING OF RURAL COMMUNITIES</strong> </p>Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ) are saddened to see that the Rural Health Alliance Aotearoa New Zealand (RHAANZ) will cease operating if it does not receive government funding next week.
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>“RWNZ supports the work already done by RHAANZ in bringing together various rural groups and rural health providers to develop initiatives for rural communities,” says RWNZ Board Member and Health Portfolio Convenor, Margaret Pittaway. </p>
<p>“Remarkable work has been done to deliver the Rural Health Road Map which sets out a plan and priorities for achieving healthily rural communities.</p>
<p>“Being geographically isolated, often with significant distance to the nearest town or health centre means that rural communities have an immediate need of affordable and reliable access to all health services.</p>
<p>“The Government has committed to rural proofing government policy, and RHAANZ has a vital part to play in this development – without the continuation of RHAANZ, and the work it does, rural communities will go backwards.</p>
<p>“There is no other place where issues impacting the health and wellbeing of rural communities are considered concurrently, and the loss of achievements met and efforts made by RHAANZ will be detrimental for our rural people.</p>
<p>RWNZ urges the Government to recognise the good work that has been done by RHAANZ and to support its continuation," says Mrs Pittaway. </p>
<p><strong>Ends</strong> </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>RWNZ Present at the National Rural Health Conference 2018</title>
        <date>Tuesday, April 10, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/Fiona Rural Health Conf.jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[<p>Friday, 6 April was the date of the National Rural Health Conference, held in the Pullman, Auckland.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ) presented at the Conference on the shortage of midwives currently faced by New Zealanders, particularly rural communities.To read more about the conference, you can follow their website <a href="http://www.nationalruralhealthconference.org.nz/nrhc18">here</a>.&nbsp;</p>
<p>RWNZ Board Member, and Health Portfolio Convenor, Margaret Pittaway has done substantial work in urging support for New Zealand midwives and women living and working rurally. The paper presented at the National Rural Health Conference was written by Mrs Pittaway and presented by RWNZ National President, Fiona Gower.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>To read the paper, you can download it <a href="/LiteratureRetrieve.aspx?ID=239847" title="RWNZ Presentation Rural Health Conference 2018">here</a>.&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Rescue Helicopter Decision Puts Lives At Risk</title>
        <date>Wednesday, April 11, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/youtube helicopter.jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[<p>Rural Women New Zealand has released a media release today, outlining our concern with the announcement of a proposal to curtail rescue helicopter service bases in Taupō, Rotorua and Te Anau.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Please follow this <a href="https://www.radionz.co.nz/news/national/354648/life-or-death-chopper-pilot-s-fears-over-service-redesign">link</a> to the media which we have responded to.&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Read our media release below.&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>RESCUE HELICOPTER DECISION PUTS LIVES AT RISK</strong> </p>
<p> <br> Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ) is concerned with the announcement of a proposal to curtail rescue helicopter service bases in Taupō, Rotorua and Te Anau.</p>
<p>“The closure of these bases will inevitably mean that people who are in need of immediate care are consequently waiting longer for medical attention, which is a concern”, says RWNZ Board Member and Health Portfolio Convenor, Margaret Pittaway. </p>
<p>“People traveling through, living, working or enjoying outdoor pursuits within these areas are already isolated due to the nature of the geography. </p>
<p>“With winter fast approaching, there will be harsher conditions on the roads and along tracks where accidents are more likely to happen.</p>
<p>“This decision fails to recognise the golden hour – where minutes can mean life or death.</p>
<p>“It is vital that communities and people travelling through areas which are a significant distance to major hospitals can feel safe knowing that medical care is accessible. </p>
<p>“It’s about making sure everyone has access to immediate medical care, and we are concerned that the closure of helicopter bases critically impacts on the emergency services required for travellers and our rural communities in need,” says Mrs Pittaway. </p>
<p><strong>Ends</strong> </p>(img source: www.youtube.com)
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Rustling Needs to be an Offence</title>
        <date>Monday, April 16, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/Rustling Submission 2018.JPG</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[
<p><i>(Pictured: RWNZ Board Member and National Finance Chair, Rachael Dean, and Manager of Government, Public Sector and Academic Relationships, Angela McLeod presenting to the Primary Production Committee.)</i> </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>RWNZ has released a media release about our oral submission to the Primary Production Committee on the Sentencing (Livestock Rustling) Bill. <br> </p>
<div>
 <div>
  <p>Please read the media release below. </p>
 </div>
</div>
<div>
 <div>
  <div>
   <p><strong>RUSTLING NEEDS TO BE AN OFFENCE</strong> </p>
   <p>Rural communities need solid action from Parliament’s Primary Production Select Committee on livestock rustling says Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ).</p>
   <p>“We presented our oral submission in support of the Sentencing (Livestock Rustling) Amendment Bill to the Primary Production Committee yesterday, and called for more to be done to enable and empower New Zealand’s rural communities,” says RWNZ National Finance Chair, Rachael Dean.</p>
   <p>“The Committee as a whole was supportive of the submissions which is great to see, however this support needs to be followed by actions starting with rustling being made an offence.</p>
   <p>“Secondly, there needs to be effective punishment and powers to seize, both of which will act as a deterrent to rustlers.</p>
   <p>“The current situation with rustling is simply not being dealt with adequately, and it is resulting in significant financial loss for our rural communities.</p>
   <p>“In addition to financial loss the emotional and mental wellbeing of rural families is affected by rustling which places additional stress on communities.</p>
   <p>“It is critical that legislation exists to provide adequate support and protection for our rural communities - they are the backbone of our country.</p>
   <p>“Amendments made to the Sentencing Act as proposed in this bill are crucial, however the fact remains that other pieces of legislation need to be fit-for-purpose. RWNZ wants this latter issue reported back to the House by the Select Committee,” says Ms Dean.</p>
   <p><strong>Ends</strong> </p>
  </div>
 </div>
</div>
<div>
 <div>
  <div>
   <p>Kind regards, </p>
   <p>Rural Women New Zealand <br>National Office <br>04 473 5524 <br><a href="/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" class="__cf_email__" data-cfemail="07626976726e756e627447757275666b70686a62692968756029697d">[email&nbsp;protected]</a></p>
  </div>
 </div>
</div>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Duck Hunting Season Begins This Weekend</title>
        <date>Wednesday, May 02, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/Ducks.jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[<p><strong style="font-family: inherit; font-size: inherit; font-style: inherit; font-variant-ligatures: inherit; font-variant-caps: inherit;">Rural Women New Zealand has released a media release regarding safe firearms practices this duck shooting season.</strong> </p>
<p><strong>Please read the media release below.</strong> </p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong> </p>
<strong>DUCK HUNTING SEASON BEGINS THIS WEEKEND</strong>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span>The ending of one hunting season and the start of another is a timely reminder about safety with firearms says Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ).</span> </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>“It is important that hunters remember the golden rules of firearms safety, especially given that the roar has finished for the most part, and duck shooting season starts this coming weekend,” says RWNZ National Finance Chair, Rachael Dean.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>“Understand and follow the Arms Code, particularly the seven basic rules of firearms safety, and reinforce safe use of firearms with other users – none of us want any more hunting tragedies.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>“The Arms Code has been designed to ensure safe measures and precaution when using firearms. </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>“Please, look after your personal health, be aware of those around you and your surroundings, and leave the celebrations until the shooting day is over and the firearms are safely locked away.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>“RWNZ wants everyone to be safe when hunting and gathering so that at the end of the day rural families and communities enjoy the fruits of living off the land – that which is quintessential to rural New Zealand” says Ms Dean.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Ends</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Rural Women New Zealand</p>
<p>National Office</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<a href="/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" class="__cf_email__" data-cfemail="f99c97888c908b909c8ab98b8c8b98958e96949c979783d79783">[email&nbsp;protected]</a>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>04 473 5524</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>(photo source: <i>pinterest.com</i>)</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Rural Women New Zealand/Access Community Health Scholarships are Open</title>
        <date>Monday, May 07, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/RWNZ logo 2018 (jpg).jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>RURAL WOMEN NEW ZEALAND/ACCESS COMMUNITY HEALTH SCHOLARSHIP IS OPEN</strong> </p>
<p>Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ) and Access Community Health are excited to announce that this year, they will be offering a scholarship of $3000 to a health worker who wishes to further their studies in the health and/or disability fields.</p>
<p>“We want to encourage people to pursue studies in health professions, and to miss out on doing so due to financial reasons would be a real shame,” says RWNZ National President, Fiona Gower.</p>
<p>"We are delighted to partner with Access Community Health to award the scholarship.</p>
<p>This scholarship is to recognise the importance in having trained health professionals wanting to work in rural sector, ensuring better health outcomes for our rural communities.</p>
<p>“Access Community Health is very proud of their longstanding relationship with Rural Women New Zealand, and once again we are delighted to be a sponsor of the RWNZ/Access Community Health Scholarship in 2018,” says Access Community HealthChief Executive Officer, Simon Lipscombe.</p>
<p>“We are very pleased for last year’s successful applicant Roberta Kaio, and we hope that the Scholarship awarded helps the recipient further their ongoing learning journey,” says Mr Lipscombe. </p>
<p>“RWNZ and Access Community Health look forward to reviewing the applicants – applications for the scholarship close Sunday, 1 July 2018, application forms can be downloaded off our website,” says Ms Gower.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>To find more information, visit the bursaries page of our website <a href="https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/services/bursaries.html">here</a>.&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Rural Women New Zealand Backs Government Supporting Families</title>
        <date>Wednesday, May 09, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/farm family_medium.jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[Rural Women New Zealand has released a media release following the announcement this morning that the Government are giving a funding boost to help improve child and family wellbeing.&nbsp;
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div>
 <div>
  <p>Read the relevant media <a href="https://www.stuff.co.nz/national/politics/103728452/frontline-domestic-violence-services-get-first-boost-in-10-years">here</a>.</p>
  <p>&nbsp;</p>
 </div>
</div>
<div>
 <div>
  <div>
   <p><strong>RURAL WOMEN NEW ZEALAND BACKS GOVERNMENT SUPPORTING FAMILIES</strong> </p>
   <p>The announcement this morning that the Government will be giving family violence services a boost of $76.2 million is a step in the right direction for our women and families, says Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ).</p>
   <p>“New Zealand’s rate of violence against women and children is unacceptable – it is great to see the Government increasing support services for women, families, and communities in need," says RWNZ National Chair, Penny Mudford. </p>
   <p>The Government also announced that additional funding in 2019/2020 would enable services to expand into areas where there is currently no support.</p>
   <p>“Women and children living in rural New Zealand have particular challenges and can be vulnerable to physical and psychological abuse due to their geographic and social isolation.</p>
   <p>“For some, living rurally means they are some distance from their families and whānau and do not have the support that the wider family can provide.</p>
   <p>“Family violence victims in rural New Zealand do not have the same level of access to psychological and legal support as urban women and children do, due to living rurally. </p>
   <p>“RWNZ hope that this boost announced by the Government will be used to empower our rural communities by giving women and children who are victims of violence the help and support they so badly need,” says Ms Mudford.</p>
   <p>Ends</p>
  </div>
 </div>
</div>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Census Data Collection Survey</title>
        <date>Monday, May 14, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/DSC05980.JPG</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[<p>Rural Women New Zealand are conducting a survey after receiving concerns from members who experienced difficulty when completing their 2018 Census. We would like to thank those members who contacted National Office and provided feedback on what to include in the survey. The survey should take 10 - 15 minutes to complete. Please take note that this survey is anonymous. <br> </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Complete the survey <a href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/FJC8SZ5">here</a>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Survey deadline - <strong>Friday, 25 May 2018</strong> </p>
<br>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Rural Women New Zealand Offers Full Support to Government</title>
        <date>Thursday, May 24, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/cows-1345859.jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[
<div>
 <table>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>Rural Women New Zealand has released a media release regarding our involvement to help support communities affected by the M.bovis outbreak. With 38 farms currently infected, and others under movement control, we encourage farmers to contact their local <span><a href="http://www.rural-support.org.nz/">Rural Support Trust</a></span> and visit MPI’s <a href="https://www.mpi.govt.nz/protection-and-response/responding/alerts/mycoplasma-bovis/">website</a> for advice and support. <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Read more about this <a href="https://www.stuff.co.nz/business/farming/104118490/Government-to-announce-Mycoplasma-decision-Monday">here</a>. </p> <p>Read the media release below. </p> </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div>
 <table>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td> <p><strong>RURAL WOMEN NEW ZEALAND OFFERS FULL SUPPORT TO GOVERNMENT </strong> </p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong> </p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong> Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ) has offered their full support to the Government for communities that are affected by the Mycoplasma bovis (M. bovis) outbreak. This announcement was made in a meeting earlier this week with Prime Minister Jacinda Ardern, Minister of Agriculture and Biosecurity Damien O’Connor, and Waikato dairy farmers, then reiterated with industry leaders. </p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>“Our rural communities are really hurting in this unprecedented biosecurity outbreak – it is vital they are supported throughout this response, no matter what future plan is decided next week,” says RWNZ National President Fiona Gower.</p> <p>“From what I saw on Monday and what we are hearing from our members and others in the industry, it is clear that the response to M. bovis is upsetting and we are pleased to have been able to offer our support.</p> <p>“Since 1925, RWNZ members have been the glue that holds rural communities together and nearly 100 years later we continue by working with Rural Support Trusts, visiting farming families, and offering funding for adverse events.</p> <p>“The decision to offer our full support comes from recent meetings with industry leaders and the Minister, and from our many years’ experience supporting rural communities.</p> <p>“We are pleased that RWNZ can continue our tradition of charitable giving and we look forward to working with the Government and industry to ensure rural communities are fully supported through the M. bovis outbreak,” says Ms Gower.</p> <p>Ends</p> </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</div>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Mycoplasma bovis announcement</title>
        <date>Tuesday, May 29, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/M.bovis press conference.jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[
<p><span>The Government has announced the decision of phased eradication of Mycoplasma bovis (M.bovis). The announcement was made yesterday afternoon, with Prime Minister Jacinda Ardern and Minister Damien O'Connor, alongside RWNZ National President, Fiona Gower and representatives from Federated Farmers, Beef and Lamb NZ, and Dairy NZ (pictured above).</span> </p>
<p>RWNZ encourages anyone needing assistance to contact the <a href="https://ruralwomennewzealand.cmail20.com/t/d-l-bztho-yhtthrdiui-y/"><span>Rural Support Trust</span></a> and recommends following updates from <a href="https://ruralwomennewzealand.cmail20.com/t/d-l-bztho-yhtthrdiui-j/">MPI</a>. It is important to support others in your community through this eradication phase. </p>
<p>Read below our media release following yesterday's announcement.&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="color: rgb(75, 172, 198);"><strong>RURAL WOMEN NEW ZEALAND WILL SUPPORT COMMUNITIES</strong> </p>
<p style="color: rgb(75, 172, 198);"><span>Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ) will continue to support communities following the Government’s decision on phased eradication of Mycoplasma bovis (M.bovis) from New Zealand.</span> </p>
<p style="color: rgb(75, 172, 198);">“RWNZ is collaborating with the Government, MPI, Rural Support Trust, and industry leaders to support our rural communities, families, women and children given today's decision," says RWNZ National President Fiona Gower. </p>
<p style="color: rgb(75, 172, 198);">“The decision to phase eradication of M.bovis has been made by Cabinet after consultation by Minister O'Connor with industry leaders.</p>
<p style="color: rgb(75, 172, 198);">“RWNZ is committed to ensuring there is wrap-around welfare support for those affected – we understand that high stress in times of crisis can lead to a breakdown of our social rural fabric.</p>
<p style="color: rgb(75, 172, 198);">“Strategic, regular, and thoughtful communications between decision makers, support networks, and communities is vital.</p>
<p style="color: rgb(75, 172, 198);">"By working together, we can do this," says Ms Gower.</p>
<br>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Rural Support Trust Chairperson, Neil Bateup</strong> says that Rural Support Trust and RWNZ will be working together to support our rural communities.</p>
<p>"Rural Support Trust is available 24/7 for free, confidential support on 0800 787 254. The welfare of farmers, their families and staff are of upmost importance to all of us. Do not be afraid to reach out if you need us," he says.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>For a full list of support services visit our <a href="https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/services/index.html">here</a>.&nbsp;</strong> </p>
<p><strong>Read the Prime Minister and Minister's full media release <a href="http://www.scoop.co.nz/stories/PA1805/S00371/plan-to-eradicate-mycoplasma-bovis.htm">here</a> for further information regarding the decision. </strong> </p>
<p><strong>Read Fiona's media statement </strong><strong><a href="/LiteratureRetrieve.aspx?ID=241190"><span id="selection-marker-1">here</span></a>.</strong> </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Rural Proofing Back On the Table</title>
        <date>Thursday, June 14, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/Penelope, Fiona, Min O'Connor, Penny, Angela.jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[
<p><i>(Pictured above: Minister Damien O'Çonnor meeting with RWNZ Chief Executive Officer Penelope England, National President Fiona Gower, National Chair Penny Mudford and Manager of Government, Public Sector and Academic Relationships Angela McLeod.)</i> </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Rural Women New Zealand has released a media release supporting the recent announcement to reintegrate rural proofing into policy development. Please read the media release below.&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>RURAL PROOFING IS BACK ON THE TABLE</strong> </p>
<p>Rural Women New Zealand (RWNZ) is pleased to see rural proofing is back on the table and being included in the Government’s policy work.</p>
<p>“Understanding the impact that Government policies, service delivery and business behaviour have on our rural communities is not only vital to the success of the rural economy, it builds and maintains our rural social fabric,” says RWNZ National President, Fiona Gower.</p>
<p>“RWNZ has been calling for rural impact analyses to be carried out in both the public and private sector because decisions have, and are being made that have a detrimental effect on rural communities.</p>
<p>“As a member of the advisory group that supported the development of the Government’s new Rural Proofing Guide for Policy Development and Service Delivery Planning, RWNZ is encouraged by the final document.</p>
<p>“RWNZ will continue to work alongside the Government, its agencies and entities to ensure successful implementation of the Rural Proofing Guide.</p>
<p>“The Government’s new rural proofing policy guidelines will go a long way to alleviating poor policy development and service delivery, and RWNZ is looking forward to seeing better outcomes for rural communities,” says Ms Gower.</p>
<p>Ends</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>For further information, please contact National Office:</p>
<p><a href="/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" class="__cf_email__" data-cfemail="c2afa7a6aba382b0b7b0a3aeb5adafa7acacb8ecacb8">[email&nbsp;protected]</a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>National Office welcomes new team members.</title>
        <date>Thursday, June 14, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/Maree Myers.jpg</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[<p>National Office welcome on board three new members to our team. Maree Myers will be working as PA to the Board and Chief Executive Officer, and Katie and Mehreen have come to us from the United States as policy interns for an eight week period. We look to working with them.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="color: rgb(75, 172, 198); font-size: 16px;"><strong>Maree Myers</strong> </p>
<p><strong><span class="CSJM-image-replacement" data-src="https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/Maree Myers.jpg?Action=thumbnail&algorithm=fill_proportional&width=310"></span><br></strong> </p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong> </p>
<p><strong>Assistant to the RWNZ Board and Chief Executive Officer</strong> </p>
<p>Maree has worked at Parliament for five different political parties including Labour, Progressive, National, Maori and NZ First.During this time, she was in six Minister’s offices as a ministerial/private secretary, EA to the NZ First Whip and recently as receptionist/admin support in the National Leader’s Office (Rt Hon Bill English).Prior to these roles, Maree worked for Sir Graeme Harrison, Managing Director, ANZCO and E J Tonks, Managing Director, Independent Casing Company as a personal assistant.</p>
<p>Maree is interested in running and has completed both the New York and Paris marathon, together with half marathons throughout New Zealand.She has also participated in the 2015 ¼ Iron Maori.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>To contact Maree, you can reach here at <a href="/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" class="__cf_email__" data-cfemail="2845495a4d4d0645514d5a5b685a5d5a49445f47454d464652064652">[email&nbsp;protected]</a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="font-size: 16px; color: rgb(75, 172, 198);"><strong>Katie Fell</strong> </p>
<p><strong><span class="CSJM-image-replacement" data-src="https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/IMG_5930.jpg" ></span><br></strong> </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Policy Intern</strong> </p>
<p>Completing a Bachelor of Arts in Politics, Philosophy, Economics and Law/Leadership Studies</p>
<p>Katie has recently finished her second year at the University of Richmond. While she studies in Virginia, her home is Chatham, New Jersey, where she has lived with her family for her whole life. At school, she is on track to complete a double major in Politics, Philosophy, Economics, and Law (PPEL) and Leadership Studies. She hopes to attend law school upon graduation. Katie is also a passionate traveler. Last summer, she completed a study abroad programme in La Rochelle, France, where she lived for six weeks. She plans on spending her upcoming semester in London, England, where she will be studying and traveling for four months.</p>
<p>She is working as a Policy Intern at the Rural Women New Zealand National Office. She is currently working on creating a policy register and planning for the RWNZ Summit in November. On her first day, she was lucky enough to sit in on the M.bovis announcement press conference led by Prime Minister Jacinda Ardern. So far her internship has been equally exciting and eye-opening.</p>
<p>Katie is hardworking, open-minded, and incredibly appreciative of the opportunity to work at Rural Women New Zealand. She looks forward to learning more throughout the internship and helping RWNZ achieve its goals.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>If you want to contact Katie, you can reach her at <a href="/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" class="__cf_email__" data-cfemail="1972786d707c377f7c7575596b6c6b78756e76747c77776337776337">[email&nbsp;protected]</a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="color: rgb(75, 172, 198); font-size: 16px;"><strong>Mehreen Usman</strong> </p>
<p><span class="CSJM-image-replacement" data-src="https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/IMG_5925.jpg"></span> <br> </p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong> </p>
<p><strong>Policy Intern</strong> </p>
<p>Completing a Bachelor of Arts in Economics and Leadership Studies </p>
<p>Mehreen is a current student at the University of Richmond in Virginia, USA studying Economics and Leadership Studies. After her undergraduate education she plans on attending law school and pursuing a career in the human rights sector. Mehreen is very excited to be joining Rural Women New Zealand for eight weeks as a Policy Intern. Throughout her internship she will help collect policy remits and organise a policy database for the organisation.</p>
<p>She is very passionate about human rights and social justice issues, especially with women’s rights, education, and immigration. Mehreen spends her time at University volunteering for Scholars’ Latino Initiative mentoring high school students who have immigrated from Latin American countries and helping improve their English skills, apply for scholarships, and become college ready. She is also involved with the Oliver Hill Scholars, an academic scholarship given to students who are interested in building a community of learners within a multicultural environment and volunteering in the community. In her free time Mehreen enjoys playing tennis and traveling. Last summer she was able to study abroad in Argentina and the coming semester she will be studying in Prague, Czech Republic. She has really enjoyed her time so far in New Zealand and can’t wait to explore more!</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>If you want to contact Mehreen you can reach her at <a href="/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" class="__cf_email__" data-cfemail="c2afa7aab0a7a7acecb7b1afa3ac82b0b7b0a3aeb5adafa7acacb8ecacb8ec">[email&nbsp;protected]</a></p>
<br>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Green Cross Health Appoints Alison Van Wyk as CEO</title>
        <date>Friday, July 06, 2018</date>
        <img>https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/Access Community Health.png</img>
        <body>
            <![CDATA[
<p>Rural Women New Zealand would like to congratulate Alison Van Wyk for her appointment as CEO of Access Community Health.&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span class="CSJM-image-replacement" data-src="https://www.ruralwomen.org.nz/Alison van Wyk 2.jpg"></span> <br> </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Alison has a background in nursing and possesses sales, marketing and management experience within the pharmaceutical, medical device and healthcare supply chain markets both within New Zealand and internationally. Instrumental in establishing professional programmes of clinical care and advice in pharmacy and the reclassification of medicines for Green Cross Health, Alison has taken a leadership role in advocacy for pharmacy and government relations within the health industry.</p>
<p>Alison commenced her new role effective 18 June 2018.</p>
<br>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
        </body>
    </post>
</news>
